Long ago, Inazuma had five legendary poets
Lúc đó, Inazuma có năm nhà thơ rất nổi tiếng
People bestowed upon them the title of The Five Kasen
Thế nhân kính nể gọi là Ngũ Ca Tiên
One Year
Một năm
The poet Suikou made his way to Tenshukaku
Suikou đến Thiên Thủ Các diện kiến
And presented the Kasen's work for the Shogun's perusal
Đem tập thơ dâng cho đại nhân bình phẩm
But a page from the works of Aoi no Okina had been torn out
Nào ngờ trong tập thơ của Aoi no Okina có một trang đã bị xé đi
And Suikou was questioned regarding the matter
Suikou vì thế mà bị tra hỏi
Suikou pleaded guilty
Suikou cúi đầu xin nhận hết tội lỗi
He admitted to drinking at the tavern the night before
Bẩm rằng tối hôm qua trong lúc hào hứng nên đã quá chén
And vaguely recalled a mysterious figure approaching while he was intoxicated
Trong cơn say, dường như có bóng người đến bên cạnh
That figure was none other than Aoi no Okina himself
Người đó cũng chính là Aoi no Okina
This turn of events had begun with an unnamed individual
Chuyện rắc rối này bắt nguồn từ một người lạ mặt
Under whose coercion Aoi no Okina was forced
Aoi no Okina bị hắn ép buộc
To take drastic measures to retrieve a page of poetry
Nên đành phải dùng thủ đoạn để lấy lại trang thơ
He knew nothing
Còn về duyên cớ vì sao người này làm vậy
All he knew was that
Thì anh ấy cũng không hề biết
The poem had to do with an old acquaintance, Akahito
Chỉ biết rằng nội dung đoạn thơ
Akahito had once belonged to the Five Kasen
Akahito từng là một nhà thơ trong Ngũ Ca Tiên
Each poem he composed, he marked with a scarlet red seal
Mỗi lần sáng tác thơ mới đều sẽ để lại dấu ấn đỏ của mình
Hence the "Aka" in his name
Nên tên của anh cũng từ đó mà ra.
Such a distinguished writer was he
Một người giỏi thơ văn như thế
And yet one of the poems he had submitted the previous year
Mà trong tập thơ được dâng lên vào năm ngoái
Was found to be plagiarized
Lại có một bài đạo thơ của người khác
Akahito was exiled for his crimes
Akahito vì thế mà bị lưu đày
And only four of the Five Kasen remained
Ngũ tiên năm người, nay chỉ còn bốn
Sumizome went over Akahito's poems
Sumizome tìm đọc hết tất cả thơ của Akahito
And noticed that the plagiarized poem lacked his seal
Chỉ thấy riêng tác phẩm đạo nhái là thiếu mất con dấu
She immersed his poetry in a stream nearby
Bèn đem tập thơ của Akahito ngâm vào dòng suối
And only on the plagiarized poem
Chỉ riêng bài đạo thơ đó
Did the ink run
Bị nước cuốn trôi vết mực
Aoi no Okina passed by
Aoi no Okina đi ngang qua đó
And witnessed Sumizome's doing
Nhìn vật nhớ người
Which he then recorded in a poem
Liền đem những chuyện nhìn thấy đưa vào trong thơ
Thus transpired the events of Suikou's poetry submission
Thế là
And this is where the story comes to an end
Một trận sóng gió đã chực chờ tại đây